<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the proceedings of His Majesties ecclesiastical commissioners, against the Bishop of London and the fellows of Magdalen-College</title>
            <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202803</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12744520</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12744520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 376:22 or 376:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the proceedings of His Majesties ecclesiastical commissioners, against the Bishop of London and the fellows of Magdalen-College</title>
                  <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
                  <author>Hedges, Charles, Sir, 1649 or 50-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 78 [i.e. 70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Milbourn, and published by Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Authorship attributed to H. Care; sometimes attributed to C. Hedges. Cf. NUC pre-1956; BM; Wing.</note>
                  <note>The only variation between copies in positions 22 and 23 on Reel 376 consists of a different catchword on p. 8 in each copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library and Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Ecclesiastical Commission (1686)</term>
               <term>Magdalen College (University of Oxford)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:93197:1"/>
            <p>Let this be Printed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sunderland</hi> P.</signed> 
               <dateline>WHITE-HALL, <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 21<hi rend="sup">st.</hi> 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Vindication OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF His Majeſties Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners, <hi>Againſt the Biſhop of</hi> London <hi>and the Fellows of</hi> Magdalen-<hi>College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Milbourn,</hi> and Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93197:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93197:2"/>
            <head>A Vindication OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF His Majeſties <hi>Eccleſiastical Commiſſioners,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The <hi>Introduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Proceedings of His MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY's <hi>Eccleſiastical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,</hi> being Made the Common Talk of the Town, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93197:3"/>Colledge have been ſuſpended, and Expelled for their Diſobedience, and Contempt to His <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> it's become Neceſſary to give the World a Juſt and Naked <hi>State</hi> of this whole Affair, to the end they may ſee, what <hi>Manner of Men</hi> Our <hi>Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Clergy, and their <hi>Creatures</hi> are; For, on an Impartial Diſquiſition into the Whole of this Matter, 'twill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> has taken ſpecial Care, that His Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners do not Exerciſe the Regal Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in that ſevere Way, the Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> has done againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters.</p>
               <p>The KING Remembreth the Promiſe He has made of Protecting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law Eſtabliſhed, and hitherto has done Nothing that Contradicts it; but has been ſo very Tender in this Point,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93197:3"/>as not to go ſo Far, as Juſtly He might; and whoever will but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Senſe Our Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Divines, and Lawyers have had of His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick Supremacy</hi> will ſoon ſee, that it's not eaſie for the Church of <hi>England</hi> to Speak againſt the Authority of His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Commiſſioners, or the <hi>Legality</hi> of their Proceedings, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Condemning Themſelves, for what they have done againſt the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans.</hi> The Caſe, in ſhort, will be brought to this; Either the Church of <hi>England</hi> has moſt Unjuſtly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd the Old Puritans; Or, the KING has very Righteouſly Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and Expell'd the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>The Agreement between what the KING has done, and the Church
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93197:4"/>of <hi>England-Law,</hi> is ſo Exact and Full, that it's impoſſible for Our <hi>Church-Men</hi> to Vindicate the Practices of their Biſhop, and <hi>Magdalen</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, without Tearing up the very <hi>Foundations</hi> of Their Own Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Conſtitution. And notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Clamour theſe Men make, the Court Held by the KING's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, and Viſitors, will appear to be Grounded on the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>-Law, and ſo are the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Inſtances before Us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93197:4"/>
               <head>Section I. <hi>The</hi> Legality <hi>of the Court, Held by His</hi> MAJESTIES <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for the <hi>COURT,</hi> Held by the KING's Eccleſiaſtical Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, though it's Said to be Contrary to the Expreſs Words of a Law lately Made, yet, on a Conſiderate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the Whole Matter; the Caſe plainly is thus: Before the 1st. <hi>Eliz.</hi> it is Agree'd, That all Ordinaries, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Judges whatſoever, Ought in all Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes to have Proceeded according to the Cenſures of the <hi>Church,</hi> and could not in any Caſe have Puniſhed any Delinquent by <hi>Fines,</hi> or <hi>Impriſonments,</hi> unleſs they had Authority ſo to do by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi> The <hi>Papal</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did never <hi>Fine</hi> or <hi>Impriſon</hi> in any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93197:5"/>Caſe, but ever Proceeded <hi>Onely</hi> by Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Cenſures. But in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> Proceeded to Fine, and Impriſon; and that by Force, as was then Suggeſted, of the Statute 1ſt. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> This <hi>Act</hi> was therefore Conſulted, and the <hi>Common-Lawyers</hi> Differ'd from the <hi>Civilians,</hi> the Former Holding, that This Law gave no Countenance to the Opinion of thoſe, who ſaid that it Impowered the Eccleſiaſtick Commiſſioners to Fine, and Impriſon. And My L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Part 4. c. 74.</note> Ch. Juſtice <hi>Coke,</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> doth with the greateſt Clearneſs Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, That the Expreſs Letter and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 1ſt. <hi>Eliz.</hi> is to <hi>Reſtore</hi> to the <hi>Crown the Ancient Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> and no Commiſſioner by Force of that Antient Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Juriſdiction could impoſe Fine, and Impriſonment; that theſe Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, having their Force from this Act <hi>of Reſtitution,</hi> cannot Inflict any ſuch Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. However, the Commiſſioners did Proceed in all Caſes to Fine, and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and, exceeding the Bounds of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cenſure, did Oppreſs, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine ſo many thouſand Families, that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93197:5"/>
                  <hi>Parliament</hi> in the <hi>Seventeenth</hi> Year of <hi>CHARLES</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> took Notice of it, and Declared in the Preamble of that Statute,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Whereas, by Colour of Some</hi> WORDS <hi>in the Aforeſaid Branch of</hi> Firſt Eliz. <hi>whereby Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners are Authorized to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their Commiſſion according to the Tenour, and Effect of the</hi> KING's <hi>Letters Patents, and by Letters Patents Grounded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the ſaid Commiſſioners have to the</hi> Great <hi>and</hi> Inſufferable Wrong <hi>and</hi> Oppreſſion of the KING's Subjects, <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Fine, and Impriſon, and to Exerciſe</hi> Other Authority <hi>not Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Eccleſiaſtical Iurisdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> Reſtored <hi>by that Act, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Great Miſchiefs, and Inconveniencies have alſo Enſued to the</hi> KING's <hi>Subjects by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſaid Branch, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions Iſſuing thereupon, and the Executions thereof; Therefore for the Repreſſing and Preventing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93197:6"/>of the foreſaid Abuſes, Miſchiefs, and Inconveniences for Time to come,</hi> Be it Enacted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here it muſt be Noted, that the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Commiſſioners taking the Branch of 1ſt. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in another Senſe than the Common Lawyers did, and that by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſome Words in it, the Parliament Repeal'd this Branch, thus Underſtood, Forbidding all Eccleſiaſtical Judges to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Fine,</hi> or <hi>Impriſon</hi> the KING's Subjects, or tender the Oath <hi>Ex Officio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Branch of 1ſt. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being thus Repeal'd, and the <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court</hi> put down, and Care taken, that No ſuch Court be for the future Erected: 'Twas Generally Concluded,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That all Ordinary Iuriſdiction was Taken from the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Vicar-Generals, Or any other perſon, or perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Exerciſing Spiritual, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Power, Authority, or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction by any</hi> Grant, Licence, <hi>or</hi> Commiſſion <hi>of</hi> the KING's <hi>Majeſty.</hi> But on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93197:6"/>the contrary it was Declared and Enacted, 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>That neither the ſaid Act of</hi> 17 Car. 1. <hi>nor any thing therein Contained</hi> Doth, <hi>or</hi> Shall <hi>take away any Ordinary Power, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from any Perſon, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Named as Aforeſaid,</hi> That is, no Authority, or Juriſdiction is, or ſhall be taken from the <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, VICAR-GENERALS,</hi> or any <hi>Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> Exerciſing Eccleſiaſtical Authority by <hi>any COMMISSION of the KING</hi>'s <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>But that They, and every of Them Exerciſing Eccleſiaſtical Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction may Proceed, Determine, Sentence, Execute and Exerciſe all manner of Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all Cenſures, and Coerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons appertaining, and belonging to the ſame, before the making of the Act,</hi>
                  </hi> 17 Car. 1. <hi>in all Cauſes, and Matters belonging to Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Iuriſdiction, according to the</hi> KING's <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws, uſed and practiſed in this Realm, in as ample Manner, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93197:7"/>Form as they did, and might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully have done before the making of the ſaid Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much is Expreſs in this Statute, 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. whereby all Power, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Authority, which belonged to Archbiſhops, Biſhops, <hi>Vicar-Generals,</hi> or any other Perſons, exerciſing Authority by <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the KING</hi>'s <hi>Majeſty</hi> before the making of the 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. is Recognized to belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the abovenamed Perſons notwithſtanding any thing in the ſaid Statute to the contrary; and that therefore whatever is ſaid touching the <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court,</hi> in the following Branch, muſt be underſtood of their <hi>Fining,</hi> and <hi>Impriſoning.</hi> Thus much may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inferred from the laſt Clauſe, 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. where it is provided, <hi>That this Act, or any thing therein contained ſhall not Extend, or be conſtrued to Extend to give unto any Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or any other perſon, or perſons aforeſaid, any Power or Authority to exerciſe, execute, inflict, or determine, any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, Cenſure, or Coercion, which they might not by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93197:7"/>Law have done before the Year of our</hi> LORD, 1639. Nor <hi>to Abridge, or Diminiſh, the</hi> KING's <hi>Majeſties Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Matters</hi> and <hi>Affairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence I infer, that there is no other Power taken from the Eccleſiaſtick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, than that of <hi>Fining, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or <hi>Tendering the OATH</hi> Ex Officio. Thus much was ſuppreſs'd by 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and no more. An Eccleſiaſtical COURT exerciſing this Power was put down, and the Erecting the like for Time to come ſtrictly forbidden. But the COURT <hi>Now</hi> ſet up, is not like unto This, for it pretends not to <hi>Fine,</hi> or <hi>Impriſon,</hi> or tender the Oath <hi>Ex Officio;</hi> it keeps within the bounds of <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Cenſures, and is no more like the <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court,</hi> than
<note n="*" place="margin">The Court Held by His MAJESTIES Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Commiſſioners, is more Legal than the Biſhops Courts; <hi>This</hi> is in the KING's Name, Theirs in their <hi>Own</hi> Names only.</note> 
                  <hi>Doctors Commons</hi> is; for Vicar-Generals, or other Perſons exerciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authority by His Majeſties Commiſſion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93197:8"/>have as much Power left them, as Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, or Biſhops have.</p>
               <p>So much Touching the <hi>Legality</hi> of the COURT.</p>
               <p>The next Thing to be Conſidered, is, Their <hi>Proceſs</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>SHARP,</hi> and the <hi>BISHOP</hi> of LONDON.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93197:8"/>
               <head>Section II. <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> LONDON's <hi>CASE fairly Stated, and Examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE State of the Biſhop's <hi>CASE</hi> I will give You in the Anſwer, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Made to the Commiſſioners, when he was Asked by the <hi>Court,</hi> Why <hi>He had not Obeyed his MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi>'s <hi>Command for Suſpending</hi> Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> which is as followeth. <hi>To the Queſtion, that was Propoſed to Me by Your Lordſhips,</hi> viz. <hi>Why did You not obey the</hi> KING's <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in his Letter concerning the Suſpending Dr.</hi> Sharp.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93197:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>I</hi> Henry <hi>Biſhop of</hi> London <hi>Do Anſwer, That immediately upon the Receipt of His MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIES Letter from my</hi> Lord Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>the Tenour whereof follows,</hi> viz.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>Iames R.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>RIGHT Reverend Father in God, WE Greet You well.</hi> Whereas, <hi>WE have been Inform'd, and are</hi> fully <hi>ſatisfi'd, that Dr.</hi> John Sharp, <hi>Rectour of the Pariſh-Church of St.</hi> Giles <hi>in the Fields, in the County of</hi> Middleſex, <hi>and your Dioceſs, notwithstanding Our Late Letter to the most Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers in</hi> GOD, <hi>the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and</hi> York, <hi>&amp; Our Directions concerning Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93197:9"/>Given at Our Court at</hi> White-Hall, <hi>the</hi> Fifth <hi>of</hi> March, 1685. <hi>in the Second Year of Our</hi> Reign; <hi>yet He the ſaid Dr.</hi> Sharp, <hi>in Contempt of the ſaid Orders, hath in ſome of the Sermons he hath ſince Preached,</hi> Preſum'd to make unbecoming Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, <hi>and to</hi> Utter ſuch Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as were not Fit, <hi>or</hi> Proper for Him; endeavouring thereby to beget in the Minds of his Hearers, <hi>an</hi> evil Opinion <hi>of</hi> US, <hi>and Our</hi> Government, by Inſinuating Fears, and Jealouſies to diſpoſe them to <hi>Diſcontent, and</hi> to lead them into <hi>Diſobedience, Schiſm, and</hi> Rebellion. <hi>Theſe are therefore to Require, and Command you immediately upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt hereof, forthwith to</hi> Suſpend Him from further Preaching in any Pariſh-Church <hi>or</hi> Chappel <hi>in your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93197:10"/>Dioceſs, untill he ſhall give</hi> Us <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and Our further Pleaſure be Known herein. And for ſo doing, this ſhall be Your Warrant. And ſo WE bid You heartily Farewel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Windſor,</hi> 
                           <date>the <hi>Fourteenth</hi> Day of <hi>June,</hi> 1686.</date> in the Second Year of Our Reign.</dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>By His MAJESTIES Command, SUNDERLAND,</hi> P.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I <hi>Took the beſt Advice I could get, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> Suſpenſion <hi>of Dr.</hi> Sharp, <hi>and was Inform'd, That the Letter being Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Me as Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>to Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend a Perſon under my Juriſdiction, I was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93197:10"/>therein to Act as a</hi> Judge; <hi>it being a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Act, and that no Perſon could by Law, be puniſhed by Suſpenſion, before he was Called, or without being Admitted to make his Defence; I thought it therefore my Duty, forthwith Humbly to Repreſent ſo much to my</hi> Lord Preſident, <hi>that ſo I might Receive His</hi> MAJESTIES <hi>Farther <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in that Matter. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that I might Obey His MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>Commands, as far as by Law I could, I did then ſend for Dr.</hi> Sharp, <hi>and Acquainted Him with His MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>
                           <hi>Diſpleaſure,</hi> and the Occaſion of it, by ſhewing him His MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>Letter; But he having never been Called to Anſwer any ſuch Matter, or make his Defence, and he Proteſting his Innocence, and likewiſe Declaring himſelf moſt Ready to give His</hi> MAJESTY <hi>full Satisfaction therein, in Order thereto, I Adviſed him to forbear Preaching, untill he had Applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to His MAJESTY; and at his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, I made him the Bearer of a Letter to my</hi> Lord Preſident, <hi>Waiting for His MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi>'s <hi>further Orders to Proceed againſt him</hi> Judicially, <hi>in caſe, he ſhould not at that Time give His</hi> MAJESTY <hi>the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93197:11"/>Required, and the ſaid Doctor hath not ſince Preached within my Dioceſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>H. <hi>London.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>That we may Rightly Underſtand the whole of this Caſe, it muſt be obſerv'd, That His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> received ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> as did fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy Him of the Truth of the Charge; That the Charge it ſelf is of a very high Nature, containing in it, not only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Letter, ſent the two Archbiſhops, and Orders, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Directions concerning Preachers; But, <hi>That by his Preaching, he endeavoured to beget in the Minds of his Hearers,</hi> an <hi>evil Opinion of His MAJESTY,</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> by inſinuating Fears, and Jealouſies to diſpoſe them to <hi>Diſcontent,</hi> and lead them into <hi>Diſobedience, Schiſm,</hi> and <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion:</hi> A Crime, which moſt undoubtedly deſerves an <hi>Ipſo Facto Suſpenſion,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Opinion of all the Judges, in the <hi>Second</hi> Year of <hi>JAMES</hi> the <hi>First,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93197:11"/>is an <hi>Offence Fineable</hi> at <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> and <hi>very near to Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>Felony in the Puniſhment.</hi> Thus it was Reſolv'd in the <hi>Puritans</hi> Caſe, who intimated in a Petition to the KING, That if He deny'd their Sute, many Thouſands of His Subjects would be <hi>Diſcontented;</hi> and the Reaſon why they thus Reſolved was,
<note n="*" place="margin">Crookes Reports <hi>an.</hi> 2 Jac. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe ſuch Petitions tended to the Raiſing of Sedition, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and Diſcontent amongſt the People.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe Juſtices ſufficiently Declare, That what tends to the Raiſing Sedition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and Diſcontent, is an Offence Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neable at Diſcretion, and very near to Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Felony in the Puniſhment: And if His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> would have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt Doctor <hi>Sharp</hi> according to the Method theſe Church of <hi>England</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have directed unto againſt <hi>Puritans,</hi> the Doctors Offence muſt have been made a Matter Criminal worthy of open Shame; and in which Caſe His <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a tender Reſpect unto the Clergy, muſt have found it neceſſary to
<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Ridle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s</hi> View, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.</note> Degrade the Doctor, whereupon, a <hi>Deprivation</hi> from his Eccleſiaſtical Benefice would have followed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93197:12"/>But his <hi>MAJETY,</hi> to ſhew the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarineſs of His Compaſſion to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> takes a milder Courſe, Commanding the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> only to <hi>Suſpend</hi> him: And yet the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and his Learned Counſel think it, not only <hi>Hard,</hi> but <hi>Illegal.</hi> For ſaith the Biſhop, <hi>I was informed, That the Letter being Directed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, as Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>I was therein to Act as</hi> a Judge, <hi>it being a Judicial Act, and that no Perſon could by Law be Puniſhed by</hi> Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>before he was Call'd, or without being Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to make his Defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then lies the Streſs of His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Plea, which will be found to lean on a very manifeſt Miſtake. For the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, obſerving in the KING's Letter a Command to Suſpend the Doctor for a Crime ſo very great, as this mention'd in the ſaid Letter (Of the Truth of which, the KING aſſures him He is fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) ought to have taken it for granted, that Doctor <hi>Sharp</hi> had incurred an <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Suſpenſion, and that 'twas his <hi>MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY</hi>'s Pleaſure, that he ſhould Denounce
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93197:12"/>him Suſpended; which the Biſhop, not as a <hi>Judge,</hi> but as a <hi>Party</hi> engag'd in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Canon, was bound to do.</p>
               <p>The Doctor's Offence then (thus preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) is very great, and His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines Himſelf within the Circle of Clemency, in that He deals with him in an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Way, and proceeded no further than to conſider him to be <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Suſpended; and if <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Suſpenſions be, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Our Church of <hi>England</hi>-Laws Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, the Biſhop's inſiſting on the neceſſity of his Acting as a <hi>Judge</hi> in a judicial way cannot help him. It hath been my part therefore to examine, <hi>Whether</hi> Ipſo Facto <hi>Suſpenſions be agreeable to the Eccleſiaſtick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> now <hi>in force;</hi> and <hi>what manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs muſt be Obſerv'd where they are Incurr'd:</hi> And on Enquiry, I find, that as the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> generally, ſo <hi>Lindwood</hi> in particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes thoſe Cenſures that are <hi>à Jure</hi> from what are <hi>ab Homine,</hi> and the Sentence <hi>à Jure lata</hi> from what is <hi>ab Homine ferenda,</hi> concluding, that a Judicial Proceſs is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, when the Delinquent is faln under the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93197:13"/>Sentence <hi>à Jure;</hi> and that therefore he Ordinary, Chancellor, or Arch-deacon, whoſe work it is to declare ſuch as are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> Excommunicated, or Suſpended to be ſo, do not then act as <hi>Judges,</hi> but as <hi>Parties</hi> engag'd in the Defence of Eccleſiaſtick Laws.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Conſtitutions of <hi>Stephen</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> it's ordain'd, That
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Decernimus ne Archidiaconi vel Officiales eorum Sententias Excommunicationis, Suſpenſionis, vel interdicti in aliquem aude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant promulgare, ubi exceſſus non eſt</hi> Manifeſtus, <hi>niſi monitione Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonica praecedente.</hi> Lindwood conſtit. Provin. de Sentent. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. c. <hi>ut</hi> Archidiac.</note> no Arch-deacons, nor their Officials preſume to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Sentences of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication or Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, or Interdict, on any without previous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition: But where the Crime is <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> they may pronounce theſe Sentences: And it muſt be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That by
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hic ſcias quod Manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt publica ſeu famoſa inſinuatio vel proclamatio &amp; communis ex certa ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; a certis Auctoribus proveniens,</hi> nondum judicialiter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſa. <hi>Lindwood</hi> ubi ſupr. in verb. Manifeſtum.</note> 
                  <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> We are to underſtand what is clear, antecedently to a <hi>Judicial</hi> Proceſs.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93197:13"/>
               <p> Beſides, <hi>Lindwood</hi> expreſly affirms, That where the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior fert ſententiam Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicationis in vim Statuti, non eſt aliqua monitio neceſſaria.</hi> Ubi ſupr.</note> Superiour declares the Sentence in <hi>Force</hi> of the <hi>Canon,</hi> there is no need of a previous Admonition.</p>
               <p>Again, where the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Excommunicatio fertur in vim ſententioe &amp; Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans procedit ut pars, quae jura ſua defendit muerone Spirituali, quod ſatis licet, non eſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea monitio.</hi> Ubi ſupr.</note> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in <hi>Force</hi> of the <hi>Statute,</hi> and he that doth Excommunicate, acts as a <hi>Party,</hi> who with the Spiritual Sword defends the Laws of the Church, which is Lawful enough for him to do, Admonition is not neceſſary. But, when the Superiour acts as a <hi>Judge,</hi> then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is oblig'd to obſerve a Legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
               <p>But the thing I would inculcate, is this, That by the Canon Law, a <hi>Penalty</hi> may be inflicted without a Hearing <hi>Parties;</hi> and that, Becauſe it is Decreed <hi>à Jure,</hi> and the Delinquent incurs it <hi>Ipſo Facto.</hi> This is the meaning of the many <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and Suſpenſions, that are Decreed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93197:14"/>by thoſe very <hi>Canons</hi> embrac'd by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> at which time the Biſhop is not to act as a <hi>Judge,</hi> but as a Part, <hi>Quae Jura ſua defendit Mucrone Spirituali.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether, what
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Duct. Dubit.</hi> lib 3. c. 2. r. 2. n. 14.</note> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> Affirms, when he aſſures us, That he who incurs a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty <hi>Ipſo Facto,</hi> is bound to be his own Executioner (Seeing whatever their Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may be, none are ſo forward, as to Execute it on themſelves) be true, or no; yet according to Church of <hi>England</hi>-Principles, we may aver, That when any do incur Excommunication, or Suſpenſion <hi>Ipſo Facto,</hi> the Ordinary, Archdeacon, or his Officials may, without <hi>Hearing Parties,</hi> pronounce it, and take care to ſee, that it be done; and if the Ordinary Command, the Archdeacon, who is Sworn to render Canonical Obedience, muſt do it. That when the Sentence is <hi>à Jure lata</hi> in ſome Caſes it's requiſite, that either the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, or ſome other do alſo <hi>Pronounce</hi> it I grant; for in the Conſtitution made by <hi>Boniface,</hi> Arcbhiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> thoſe who were <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Excommunicated,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93197:14"/>muſt by the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Per locorum Ordinarios pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice Excommunicati nuncientur.</hi> Lindw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d provin. conſtit. de foro compell. c. contingit. ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando.</note> Ordinaries of the place be declared to be ſo; but then 'tis
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non opus eſt monitione in hoc caſu ſed ſola citatione ut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant allegaturi cauſam rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem, quare declarari non debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant incidiſſe in dictam ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> Ubi ſupr. in verb. Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatur.</note> without any <hi>previous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,</hi> it's only need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that the Delinquent be cited to Appear, and ſhew Cauſe why he ſhould not be declared Excommunicate; and no more can be ſaid of <hi>ipſo facto</hi> Suſpenſions, where the Sentence is <hi>à Jure ſeu Canone;</hi> and the utmoſt that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, is only, That theſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nec etiam Excommunicare poteſt &amp; hoc verum in eo, qui eſt ſuſpenſus</hi> ab Homine, <hi>vel etiam</hi> a Canone, <hi>ſi ſit publice denunciatus, alioquin in ſuſpenſo</hi> a Canone <hi>non denuntiato, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu toleratur in ſuo ſtatu valet quod per eum agitur.</hi> Lindw. prov. l. 1. tit. 2. de conſtit. c. Quia in.</note> Suſpenſions be <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly</hi> Denounced: For, as <hi>Lindwood,</hi> if an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary be Suſpended <hi>à Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none,</hi> he cannot Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, if it be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; but otherwiſe he may.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice to prove, That to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Biſhop to Suſpend; that is, To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce one Suſpended without a Judicial Proceſs, is conform to the Conſtitutions em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93197:15"/>by the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and in this Caſe the Biſhop is bound to Obey, if Commanded by the Supreme Ordinary. And although ſome very boldly Affirm, That theſe Suſpenſions are contrary to the Laws of GOD, of Nature, and of Nations: yet nothing hath been more commonly practis'd by the Church of <hi>England</hi> in their proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Diſſenters than <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are of a like kind with <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Suſpenſions, for both are without a <hi>Judicial</hi> Proceſs; and at this very time <hi>Ipſo Facto De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privations,</hi> which are more than <hi>Suſpenſions ab Officio,</hi> are eſtabliſhed by our Laws.</p>
               <p>By the Statute of 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. If an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, having a Benefice with Cure of Souls, value <hi>Eight Pound per Annum,</hi> take another with Cure, immediately after In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction thereunto, the former is void, even without any <hi>Declaratory Sentence</hi> of Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in the Eccleſiaſtical Court. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever neglects to Read <hi>The Articles of Religion</hi> within two Months next after <hi>Induction,</hi> he is deprived <hi>Ipſo Facto;</hi> and upon ſuch Avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, there is no need of a <hi>Sentence Declaratory.</hi> And if this be not contrary to the Laws of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93197:15"/>GOD, nor of our Land, How comes it to paſs, that an <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> Suſpenſion ſhould be ſuch a hideous thing in the eſteem of a Church of <hi>England</hi>-Man, who has been ſo accuſtomed to treat the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> after this very way and manner?</p>
               <p>On the whole then, I hope it's ſufficiently clear'd, That the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> in the preſent caſe, was bound to Obey His <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY,</hi> and Suſpend the Doctor; That the Capitulation he enter'd into with his Prince, and the Contempt of His <hi>Authority,</hi> deſerv'd no leſs than a Suſpenſion <hi>ab Officio.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:93197:16"/>
               <head>Section III. <hi>A Juſt Account of the Proceedings of the</hi> Commiſſioners <hi>Appointed by His</hi> MAJESTY <hi>under the Great Seal for Viſiting St.</hi> Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len <hi>College in</hi> Oxford.</head>
               <p>ON the Death of Dr. <hi>Clark,</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> before the day of Election the KING ſends down a <hi>Mandamus</hi> for the Electing another; and whereas, the Fellows were Sworn to obſerve the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege Statutes, which oblig'd them to Chooſe one of their Own, or of New College, His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> ſends down a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> with His <hi>Mandatory Letter;</hi> notwithſtanding which, the Fellows pretending, that they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93197:16"/>were bound in Conſcience to obſerve the Statute, becauſe of their Oaths, regard not the Mandatory Letter, nor Royal Diſpenſation; They make not a Choice as the KING Commanded, and when cited before His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Commiſſioners, and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, to Anſwer for their Diſobedience, they in a moſt Contemptuous Manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt the Proceedings.</p>
               <p>The Great Points therefore to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, may be Reduced to theſe two Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Whether the KING by His Prerogative may not Diſpenſe with the College</hi> Statutes?</item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Whether, when there is a</hi> Diſpenſation <hi>Granted, the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows are by their Oath Obliged
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93197:17"/>to Act according to thoſe very Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that are Diſpenſed with?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>A <hi>Solution</hi> to Theſe <hi>Queſtions</hi> will be <hi>Sufficient</hi> to Clear the Truth in this Affair; for if the Diſpenſation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Church of <hi>England-Law</hi> be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, and the Fellows are not by their Oaths Bound to obſerve the Statutes after ſuch a Diſpenſation, 'twill unavoidably follow, That the <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Fellows have been moſt juſtly Suſpended and Expell'd. And thus much will be with much clearneſs evinced.</p>
               <div n="1" type="solution">
                  <head>I. <hi>Touching the <hi>Diſpenſing Power.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The KING's Power in Matters Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical is ſo very ample, and extenſive, that it's not eaſy for any one to ſet bounds, or limits to it; By our Common Lawyers it hath been often affirmed, <hi>That whatever the Pope</hi> de facto <hi>formerly did within this Realm
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93197:17"/>by the Canon Law,</hi> that of Right <hi>belongs to our KINGS.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And on this Ground it has been adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the <hi>Legiſlative Power</hi> in Matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical is lodged in the <hi>KING.</hi> The <hi>Pope</hi> made Laws for the Government of the Clergy; and ſo may the <hi>KING:</hi> And thus much Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as ſupreme Head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> on the Requeſt of Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> exerciſed, when ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a Subſcription to the three Articles, and depriv'd thoſe who would not Obey. The Statute of 13 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 12. required Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to the <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of the Sacraments <hi>onely;</hi>
                     </hi> and with this, thoſe, who preached againſt Ceremonies, and the Hierarchick Government, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whitgift</hi> therefore, and the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Commiſſioners go further, and by the Regal Power ordained Subſcription to the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, and depriv'd ſuch as refuſed to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. In the Firſt of K. <hi>James</hi> I. theſe Articles are Eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Canons,</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93197:18"/>without an Act of Parliament, made in that Year, on which occaſion Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were very Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick
<note n="*" place="margin">We complain, That we are put out from our Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which are a <hi>Freehold</hi> by the bare and ſole Sentence of a Biſhop; whereas the Liberty of an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> is this, To be put from his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold by none but by the Verdict of Twelve Men. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> on the Croſs, <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>P.</hi> 108.</note> Clamours as great, yea, ſo great, that the Clergy judg'd it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to beſeech His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all the Juſtices of <hi>England</hi> to confer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this thing, and give in their opinion, which accordingly they did; For it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded by the Lord Chancellour,
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Crokes</hi> Reports, <hi>an.</hi> 2. <hi>Jacob</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Whether the Deprivation of the Puritan Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for refuſing to conform themſelves to the Ceremonies appointed by the laſt Canons,</hi> was Lawful? They all anſwered, <hi>That they had conferred thereof before, and held it to be Lawful, becauſe the KING has the</hi> Supreme Eccleſiaſtical Power.— <hi>And they held it clear, that the KING, without a Parliament, might make Orders and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Government of the Clergy, and might deprive them, if they Obey not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:93197:18"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Civilians</hi> go higher, affirming, That the KING, as Supreme, is <hi>Himſelf</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead <hi>of the Whole Law;</hi> yea, that he is the <hi>Law it Self,</hi> and the Only Chief In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter thereof, as in whoſe Breaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the whole Knowledge of the ſame. And that His <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> by commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating His Authority to His Judges, to Expound the Laws, doth not thereby ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the ſame from Himſelf. Theſe, with <hi>Borellus,</hi> do hold,
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ridley</hi> view, p. 2. c. 1. ſect. 7.</note> That <hi>Principum placita legis habent vigorem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as the KING, by the Fulneſs of His Eccleſiaſtical Power can, <hi>without a Parliament,</hi> make what Laws He Pleaſe for the Government of the Clergy; in like manner, The <hi>Power of the KING,</hi> in Matters Eccleſiaſtical, is too ample to be <hi>limited by an Act of Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93197:19"/>
                  <p> Thus much has been clear'd up by my Lord
<note n="*" place="margin">part. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Coke,</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> where he tells us, <hi>That albeit the Acts of</hi> 24 Hen. 8. &amp; 25 Hen. 8. <hi>do, upon certain Appeals, make the ſentence Definitive, as to any Appeal; for the Words be</hi> [ſhall be Definitive] <hi>and that no further Appeal ſhould be had, yet the</hi> KING, <hi>after ſuch a</hi> Definitive Sentence, <hi>as</hi> Supreme Head, <hi>may grant a Commiſſion of Review,</hi> ad Revidendum, &amp;c. — <hi>for that after a</hi> Definitive Sentence, <hi>the Pope, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head, by the Canon Law, uſed to grant a Commiſſion</hi> ad Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum.—<hi>And ſuch Authority as the Pope had, claiming as Supreme Head, doth of Right belong to the Crown, and is annexed thereunto by the Statutes of the</hi> 26 Hen. 8. c. 1.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93197:19"/>&amp; 1. Eliz. c. 1. <hi>And ſo it was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in the</hi> Kings-Bench, Trin. 39 Eliz. <hi>where the Caſe was, That Sentence being given in an Eccleſiaſtical Cauſe in the Countrey, the Party grieved appeal'd according to the ſaid Act of</hi> 25 Hen. 8. <hi>to the Archbiſhop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the firſt Sentence was affirmed: Whereupon, according to the Statute of</hi> 25 Hen. 8. <hi>he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to the Delegates. And upon this matter a Prohibition was prayed in the</hi> King's-Bench, <hi>pretending that the Commiſſion of Review was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law, for that the Sentence before the Delegates was Definitive by the Statute of</hi> 25 Hen. 8. <hi>But upon Mature Deliberation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the Prohibition was deny'd; for that the Commiſſion for the Cauſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93197:20"/>aboveſaid was reſolv'd to be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly granted. In this Caſe, I being then (ſaith Sir</hi> Edward Coke) <hi>the Queens</hi> Attorney, <hi>was of Counſel to maintain the Queens Power. And Preſidents were cited in this Court in</hi> Michelot's <hi>Caſe,</hi> Anno. 29 Eliz. <hi>and in</hi> Goodman's <hi>Caſe, and in</hi> Hewet's <hi>in</hi> 29 Eliz. <hi>alſo.</hi> So far Sir <hi>Edw. Coke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From whence it's moſt manifeſt, That an Act of Parliament can be no Bar to the Exerciſe of the Regal Power, that is eſtabliſhed by the Common Law, as the KING's Supremacy in Matters Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal is. But further,</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Grant of Diſpenſations is a Peculiar</hi> and <hi>very Conſiderable Part of Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> which is eminently Seated in the CROWN. That the ſame Power the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93197:20"/>Pope claimed in this Land, as Supreme Head, doth of Right belong to our <hi>KINGS,</hi> has been abundantly proved; and in the Statute of 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 22. it is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>That the Pope claimed full Power to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with all Humane Laws of all Realms in all Cauſes, which he called Spiritual.</hi> And my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hobart,</hi> delivering his Opinion about the Power of <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> in general, holds it clear,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Colt</hi> and <hi>Glover, ver,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Leitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That though the Statute of</hi> 25 Hen. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>ſays, That all Diſpenſations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be Granted in manner and form fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and</hi> not otherwiſe; <hi>that yet the</hi> KING <hi>is not thereby reſtrained, but his Power remains full and perfect as before, and He may ſtill Grant them as</hi> KING; <hi>for all Acts of Iuſtice and Grace flow from Him, as</hi> 4 <hi>Eliz.</hi> Dier. 211. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93197:21"/>of Tryal of Piracy upon the Statute of</hi> 28 Hen. 8 <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>is good, tho' the Chancellor do not nominate the Commiſſioners, as that Statute appoints, and yet it is a New Law. And</hi> Mich. 5. &amp; 6. Eliz. Dier. 225. <hi>The Queen made Sheriffs without the Iudges, notwithſtanding the Ninth of</hi> Edward 2. <hi>And</hi> Mich. 13. &amp; 14. Eliz. Dier. 303. <hi>The Office of</hi> Alna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>granted by the Queen, without the Bill of the Treaſurer, it is good with a</hi> non obſtante, <hi>againſt the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of</hi> 31 Hen. 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>For theſe Statutes, and the like, were made to put things in Ordinary Form, and to caſe the</hi> SOVEREIGN <hi>of Labour, but</hi> not to Deprive <hi>Him</hi> of Power.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93197:21"/>
                  <p> Beſides, the Learned of the Law do with much Plainneſs aver, and clear up thus much to Us, That the <hi>KING</hi> can Grant out what ever Diſpenſations the Pope did, ſo long as the things Diſpenſed with are not <hi>Mala in ſe.</hi> In <hi>Eccleſiaſticals</hi> the <hi>KING</hi> can Diſpenſe not only with <hi>Canons,</hi> but with <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> yea, with any thing that is but <hi>Malum prohibitum;</hi> and ſeeing the Univerſities are for the Maintenance of Religion, and fall under the Care of the Supreme <hi>HEAD,</hi> as other Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical Corporations do, the <hi>KING</hi> can in like manner Diſpenſe with their Statutes. If with the Greater, no doubt with the Leſſer. If an Act of Parliament may be Diſpenſed with, it's not to be queſtion'd, but a Provincial Canon may be ſo too; and if Acts of Parliament and Provincial Canons cannot limit, or confine,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93197:22"/>or ſtand before the <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> How is it poſſible, that a <hi>Colledge-Statute</hi> ſhould do it? To ſuppoſe that it can, is to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe greater Power to One Man, or to a little Corporation, than to the greateſt Body of the <hi>Nation;</hi> than which, nothing can be more abſurd. Beſides, the Laws enacted by the Founder of a Colledge, can have no more Strength than they receive from the <hi>KING.</hi> Nor can a Colledge be erected without <hi>His</hi> Leave.</p>
                  <p>Time would fail to produce all the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities,</hi> by which (according to Church of <hi>England</hi>-Doctrine) the <hi>Truth</hi> hereof may be Confirm'd. And this is ſo well done by other Hands, that I will ſtay no longer on it, but will go on to Conſider,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="solution">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whether, notwithstanding a Diſpenſation, thoſe who have been Sworn to Obſerve the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93197:22"/>of a Colledge, cannot Act contrary thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, without violating their Oath?</hi> For here lies the ſtreſs of what the <hi>Magdalen</hi> Gentlemen have to ſay for themſelves; and yet We can no ſooner Explicate the Nature of a <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> but may ſee how feeble the Foundation is, on which theſe Men lean in Defence of their contemptuous Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Royal Mandate.</p>
                  <p>The Nature then of a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> (as it was agreed in the caſe of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jones</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, <hi>fol.</hi> 158, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>Evan</hi> and <hi>Kiffin</hi> againſt <hi>Askwith</hi>) is <hi>to derogate,</hi> and <hi>make void a Statute, Canon,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> as to <hi>that, which it prohibits the Parties, to whom 'tis Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. It is an Exception</hi> (as to them) <hi>out of the Statute,</hi> or <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> The Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Power of the Statute or Canon, is taken away, as to that Perſon, who has the Diſpenſation.
<note n="†" place="margin">Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt mali prohibiti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vida relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> It is as to him in a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93197:23"/>manner vacated. Though the Canon, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or Conſtitution be not made ſimply void and null; yet in ſome Reſpects it is made void. As to this, or the other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for this time the Obligation Ceaſes. Here then lies the Difference between the <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> with a Law, and the <hi>Repealing</hi> it. A Repeal vacates the Law to all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and Purpoſes, but a Diſpenſation doth onely in ſome reſpect vacate it. By a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal</hi> the Law is aboliſhed, but where there is a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> onely, though the Law obliges not the Perſon for ſuch a time, yet it remains a Law ſtill. A Repeal kills it, but a Diſpenſation only binds it up, or ſtands between the Obligation of it, and this or the other Party; but ſtill as to the Party to whom the Diſpenſation is given, the Law is made void, and to him it is as if there had been no ſuch Law for that time.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:93197:23"/>
                  <p> So much touching the Nature of a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation;</hi> from whence it clearly follows, That the <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Gentlemen ſtood not bound by Oath to Chooſe according to their Statutes, for to them there remained no ſuch Statute as obliged them to chooſe one of their own Society; and they might, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Oath, act as if no ſuch thing had been. For the KING ſent 'em his Diſpenſation, which took away the ſtrength of their Statute; it laid the very Statute aſide for that ſeaſon: And this Bar being taken out of the <hi>Fellows</hi> way, His Majeſty commands them to chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and all were bound to Obey the Royal Mandate: For, they were ſworn only to the Statutes, that were in force; but the Diſpenſation taking away the force of the Statute, the Oath oblig'd them not to keep it.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93197:24"/>
                  <p> To illuſtrate this, I will ſuppoſe, that by an Act of Parliament this College-Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute had been made utterly void and null, as thoſe relating to the Maſs have been: Will any ſay, that the Fellows, becauſe of their Oath are with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> to this Act of Parliament, ſtill bound to keep to the vacated Statute? I preſume not, for Statutes made by a particular Man, or Corporation, cannot be of greater Force than an Act of Parliament; and the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege-Statute being vacated, the Oath obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them not to keep it; and for the ſame reaſon, I may boldly affirm, that ſeeing, according to Church of <hi>England-Law,</hi> the Royal Diſpenſation doth as effectually make void the Statute to theſe Men for that time, they are not obliged by their Oath to obſerve it.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93197:24"/>
                  <p> Furthermore, we find, that in proceſs of time, ſome Laws never Repeal'd wear out of date, and become uſeleſs; and though never Repeal'd, yet muſt be conſider'd as void and null, or the whole Kingdom muſt be brought under the Guilt of Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I will inſtance in one Law, which was Made <hi>Anno</hi> 3 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 3. Requiring <hi>Every Man, being the</hi> KING's <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not Lame, Decrepit, nor Maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor having any other Lawful, or Reaſonable Cauſe, or Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mént, being within the Age of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years, except Spiritual Men, Iuſtices of the One Bench, and of the Other, Iuſtices of Aſſize, and Barons of the Exchequer, to uſe, and exerciſe Shooting in Long-Bows, and alſo to have a Bow and Arrow ready continually in his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93197:25"/>Houſe to uſe, and do uſe himſelf in Shooting:</hi> Alſo, that the Father, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Rulers of ſuch as are of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Age, do teach and bring up them in the Knowledge of the ſame Shooting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, there is a Law requiring thus much, not yet Repeal'd, that I can find; and all Conſtables ſtill Swear, <hi>That they will have a Care for the Maintenance of <hi>Archery,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute.</hi> But yet it's Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that this Statute is not Obſerved, nor doth the Conſtable regard this part of his Oath. And why, But becauſe the Statute is Obſolete, and by a general Conſent grown out of uſe, and muſt be eſteemed as if it had been vacate and null. And it's moſt manifeſt, that a Diſpenſation can as effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at leaſt ſo far vacate a Statute, that the Perſon, who is otherwiſe Sworn to keep it, may without Perjury forbear it's Obſervance.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93197:25"/>
                  <p> And that this is manifeſt, where there is a Diſpenſation, appears from the Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of our Judges,
<note place="margin">See that new little Book Entituled, <hi>The Juſtices Caſe;</hi> which, if it had come out time enough, might perhaps have kept ſome of theſe <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi>-Scholars in their Places, ſuppoſing any of them pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conſcientious, that went out meerly for want of Light, about the Obligation of an Oath, which is the buſineſs of that Caſe.</note> and Juſtices of the Peace, throughout the Whole Kingdom, who, tho' Sworn to Execute the Laws, do eſteem them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Diſcharged from the Execution of thoſe lately Diſpenſed with by His Sacred MAJESTY. But,</p>
                  <p>To come Cloſer to our <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, I would propoſe to their Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the Church-Wardens Oath, which runs in theſe Words, [<hi>You ſhall ſwear Truly and Faithfully to Execute the Office of a</hi> Church-Warden, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Pariſh, and according to the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93197:26"/>beſt of your skill, and Knowledge,</hi> Preſent <hi>ſuch Things, and Perſons, as to your Knowledge are</hi> Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>by the Laws</hi> Eccleſiaſtical of this Realm.] This is the Oath, and whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is contrary to any one Canon, is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentable by the Laws Eccleſiaſtical. And if a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> be not ſufficient to excuſe the Church-Wardens from Perjury, for not Preſenting the Tranſgreſſours of the Canons, This ſort of People will not be only Perjur'd, for not Preſenting the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> at this time, but for not Preſenting ſome of the Fatteſt amongſt their own Clergy-men. For as the <hi>Civilians</hi> aſſure Us, the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Law is, <hi>That every Spiritual Perſon is Viſitable by the Ordinary,</hi> and yet the KING exempts Multitudes from the Ordinary's Viſitations. Thus formerly many <hi>Abbies</hi> have been, and now all <hi>Donatives</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93197:26"/>and the Eccleſiaſtical Law is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with; and, Muſt all thoſe who are in Donatives, and receive not Inſtitution nor Induction from the Biſhop, nor will ſubmit to the Ordinary's Viſitation, be preſented; or are the Church-Wardens Perjur'd?</p>
                  <p>Again, All <hi>Pluralities</hi> are contrary to the Canon; but if <hi>His MAJESTY</hi> gives a Diſpenſation, a Prieſt may hold two Benefices; and nothing more Common. There is alſo a <hi>Canon,</hi> That <hi>a Baſtard ſhall not be a Prieſt;</hi> however, if the KING Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes with this <hi>Canon,</hi> the Baſtard may enter into Holy Orders. But muſt the Church-Warden preſent Every <hi>Baſtard-Prieſt,</hi> and all that hold <hi>Pluralities,</hi> or elſe be For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn?</p>
                  <p>But the Caſe is too plain to need further <hi>Proof.</hi> All know, That when an Oath is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to Obſerve the Laws, it is no longer than they are in Force; If he Law be repeal'd, the Oath obliges not any to Obſerve it; and as to the Perſon Diſpenſed with, the Law for that time ſo far ceaſes, that to him, there is no
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93197:27"/>ſuch Law, and therefore his Oath binds him not in this caſe to Regard it. <hi>Effectus enim Diſpenſationis</hi> eſt <hi>auferre à particulari Perſona ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter,</hi> vel <hi>in tali tempore aut occaſione, Obligatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad Opus,</hi> vel <hi>Omiſſionem,</hi> vel <hi>poenam,</hi> vel <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre irritationem,</hi> aut <hi>inhabilitatem, quam lex ipſa efficiebat.</hi> So <hi>Salas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee, That if it be in the Power of the KING to ſuſpend the Colledge-Statutes, the Pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience about keeping to their Oath, is vain and ludicrous: For which Reaſon, I will only add one Conſideration more, to ſhew that the <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> Power leans on a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that cannot be moved, but to the Endangering the Whole Eccleſiaſtick Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as Exercis'd by the Biſhops.</p>
                  <p>'Tis well known, That what Power is Strong enough to Diſpenſe with an Act of Parliament about <hi>Civils,</hi> wants not Strength to Diſpenſe with Parliamentary Laws, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eccleſiaſtical Affairs; nor with Church-Canons, nor Colledge-Statutes. And that the KING can Diſpenſe with Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93197:27"/>relating unto Civil Affairs, is a Matter grounded on the ſame Bottom with the Biſhop's Juriſdiction; and that is, On the <hi>Opinion of the Church-of</hi>-England-<hi>Judges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it is the Opinion of our <hi>Judges,</hi> That the <hi>KING</hi> can Diſpenſe in Matters <hi>Civil,</hi> is Notorious, the Matter of Fact is very Lately become too Obvious to admit of a Denyal; and that the Biſhop's Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction has no other ground for its Support, is eaſily proved. For by the Firſt of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. it is declared, that <hi>It's contrary to Common-Law for any to Hold Courts in any other than the KING's Name.</hi> So that, whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of this Statute, whether Repeal'd, or in Force, ſeeing the Common-Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains the ſame, the Biſhops muſt have a Commiſſion from the <hi>KING,</hi> and Hold <hi>Courts</hi> in His <hi>MAJESTY'S</hi> Name, or be affirm'd to make an Invaſion on the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law,</hi> which is no leſs than a <hi>Premunire.</hi> However, the Biſhops have held Courts in their own Names ever ſince King <hi>Edward's</hi> Days; and, as the Old <hi>Puritans</hi> did imagin, their Courts were Illegal, their Biſhops
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93197:28"/>Premunir'd, and ſeveral Demurr'd to their Juriſdiction. For which Reaſon, <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt call'd all his Judges together, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to give in their Opinion touching this Matter, which they did in theſe Words:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>According to Your Lordſhips Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, made in His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> Court of</hi> Star-Chamber <hi>the</hi> 12th. <hi>of</hi> May <hi>laſt, We have taken Conſideration of the Particulars, wherein our</hi> Opinions <hi>are required by the ſaid Order; and We have All agreed, That</hi> Proceſſes may Iſſue out of Eccleſiaſtical Courts, <hi>in the Names of Biſhops; and that a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent under the Great Seal is not neceſſary,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>By this it appeareth, That the Whole Power of the Biſhop's Juriſdiction depends upon the Opinion of theſe Judges; and if theſe Judges Opinion be not more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than the Common-Law, the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Biſhops is gone. If it be, the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing-Power,</hi> grounded on the Late Opinion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93197:28"/>of the Judges, is Valid: So that the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult will be this, the Biſhop's Power muſt be Deſtroyed, or the <hi>KING</hi>'s <hi>Diſpenſing-Power</hi> muſt be Recogniz'd.</p>
                  <p>But although the Matter is ſo fully clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, in Defence of His <hi>MAJESYT</hi>'s Commiſſioners and Viſitors, yet the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Fellows, and their Contempt of the <hi>Regal Authority,</hi> exceeded all Bounds; For as they, contrary to the Royal Mandate, proceed to Elect Dr. <hi>John Hough,</hi> and although his Election was made null and void by the Commiſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, yet the Dr. refuſed to ſubmit thereunto, whereby he put the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners under a neceſſity of Expelling him the Houſe; which being done, the Doctor makes his Proteſtation againſt their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as <hi>Illegal,</hi> and <hi>Unjuſt,</hi> and <hi>Null;</hi> and this Proteſtation accompanied with a Tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Humm or Acclamation, as if the Whole Houſe had been engaged in a Conſpiracy againſt His <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> and had deſign'd the Depriving the CROWN of One of its Richeſt Jewels, <hi>viz.</hi> The Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93197:29"/>Supremacy. The Fellows alſo at firſt refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſubmit unto the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who was by His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> made their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident; but at laſt gave in this Anſwer, in Writing, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereas His MAJESTY has been Pleas'd by His Royal Authority, to cauſe the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in GOD,</hi> Samuel Lord Biſhop of Oxford, <hi>to be Inſtalled Preſident of this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, We, whoſe Names are hereunto Subſcribed, do Submit as far as is</hi> Lawful <hi>and</hi> Agreeable to the Statutes of the ſaid Colledge.</p>
                  <p>The Chaplains, and all the Members of the Society, except the <hi>Under-Porter,</hi> gave in a Paper to the ſame Effect.</p>
                  <p>But Dr. <hi>Farefax,</hi> who would not Submit unto the Suſpenſion he had incurr'd, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the Juriſdiction of the Court, for which Reaſon he was Deprived of his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip. And, notwithſtanding the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Submiſſion, theſe ſame Fellows, within three Days, brought in a <hi>Paper</hi> with all their Hands Subſcribed, of the Tenor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:93197:29"/>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Lordſhips,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WEE have Endeavoured in all Our Actions to Expreſs Our Selves with all Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to His MAJESTY, and being Conſcious to Our Selves, That in the whole Conduct of this Buſineſs before Your Lordſhips, We have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what Our Oaths and Statutes <hi>Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſably</hi> oblig'd Us to; We cannot make any Declaration, whereby We acknowledge that We have done</hi> Amiſs, <hi>as having Acted according to the Principles of Loyalty and Obedience to His Sacred MAJESTY, as far as We could, without doing Violence to Our Conſciences, or Prejudice to Our Rights (one of which We humbly Conceive that of Electing a Preſident to be), from which We are Sworn, upon no Account whatſoever, to depart. We therefore humbly Beg your Lordſhips to repreſent this Favourably, with Our Utmoſt Duty, to His</hi> MAJESTY; <hi>Whom <hi>GOD</hi> grant Long and Happily to Reign over Us.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:93197:30"/>
                  <p> On the <hi>Tueſday, October</hi> 25. 1687. they Submit; but on the <hi>Friday</hi> following, <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 28. they can't in Conſcience do it. A very ſudden, but a prodigious Change. Their Submiſſion was as much as the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours expected; for as it was to the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> their Preſident, Inſtalled by His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Royal Authority, <hi>as far as is</hi> Lawful <hi>and Agreeable to the Statute of the ſaid Colledge, this was enough;</hi> For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Church of <hi>England</hi>-Law, the <hi>KING</hi> can Diſpenſe with their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. To talk of an Indiſpenſable Statute, is to ſuppoſe it deſign'd for the Limitation of the <hi>KING</hi>'s Power in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, whereby it becomes <hi>Ipſo Facto,</hi> void and null; but there being no ſuch Statute, the Method His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> took, was ſuch as capacitated the Fellows to Obey <hi>His</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, without laying their Conſciences un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Violence. 'Twas all Fair and Legal, and their Complying ſo far ſatisfied the <hi>KING</hi>'s Viſitors.</p>
                  <p>But, as we may well conjecture, the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows having conſulted the <hi>Under-Porter,</hi> who
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93197:30"/>had either more Sence, or Honeſty than the Doctors, for he refuſed to ſubmit ſo far, perhaps knowing, that this was a <hi>full Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> they tack about, and preſume to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all that they had done in this Affair: Though they had declared, That they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Juriſdiction of the Court, and thereby endeavoured to Raviſh from the KING a peculiar Part of His Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; Though they applauded Dr. <hi>Hough,</hi> for his Proteſting againſt the Proceedings, as Illegal, Void, and Null: Yet they arrive to the Boldneſs of Averring, <hi>That in the Whole Conduct of this Buſineſs they did nothing but what their Oaths and Statutes Indiſpenſably obliged them to;</hi> and therefore cannot declare, <hi>That they have done any thing Amiſs,</hi> and make Uſe of what they have oft call'd the Old Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Cant of Regulating the Principles of their Loyalty to the <hi>KING,</hi> by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of an Oath to the Statutes of the Colledge, and with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to their own Rights.</p>
                  <p>Though the poor Diſſenters did Plead <hi>Conſcience</hi> of Duty unto <hi>GOD Only,</hi> as
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93197:31"/>what they Judged ſufficient to exempt them from Obeying their Prince in thoſe Inſtances, which Interfer'd with the <hi>KING</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; yet 'twas enough to provoke the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiſts to cenſure them <hi>Seditious, Factious, and Rebellious:</hi> But theſe Gentlemen plead <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> not that they are bound by an Heavenly Decree, they can go no higher, than to inſiſt on the <hi>Obligation</hi> of a little Colledge-Statute, that has been Diſpenſed with, and the <hi>Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of their Univerſity-Rights, as if greater Regard muſt be had to the Pretended Rights of the Church of <hi>England</hi>-Clergy and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, than to thoſe of the CROWN; and a greater Deference muſt be paid to the Vacated Statutes of their Colledge, than the <hi>Puritans</hi> might give to the Commands of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus theſe <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Gentlemen go on with a Confidence that bears ſome proportion to the Badneſs of their Cauſe, and are not afraid to caſt the Greateſt Contempt on His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Commiſſioners and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and conſequently on His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> Himſelf, whoſe Perſon they repreſent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Humbling themſelves for their many
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93197:31"/>Inſolencies, or inſtead of acting according to their <hi>Quondam</hi> avowed Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, they fly in the Face of Authority, charging it with no leſs Guilt than the <hi>Injuring</hi> a Whole Society; and, as if they had ſtill to do with their Diſſenting Brethren, they cloſe up the Scene with an <hi>Inſulting Threat:</hi> For, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Expulſion, they ſeverally gave in Papers to the Effect following.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Lordſhips,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I <hi>Do profeſs all Duty to His MAJESTY, and Reſpect to Your Lordſhips, but beg Leave to declare, I think my Self <hi>Injured</hi> in Your Lordſhips Proceedings, and therefore Proteſt againſt them, and</hi> will uſe all Juſt <hi>and</hi> Legal <hi>means of being</hi> relieved.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Here you ſee they complain of <hi>Injuries</hi> done 'em, and are reſolv'd to uſe all Juſt and Legal Means (they ſay) for their own Relief. But who can imagine what they will underſtand by Juſt and Legal Means?</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:93197:32"/>
                  <p> The Whole of theſe Proceedings depend on the Diſpenſing Power: If His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> had not Diſpenſed with their Colledge-Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, the Caſe would have been another thing; but the Diſpenſation makes it manifeſt, That no Pretence of an <hi>Oath</hi> can be ſufficient to excuſe their <hi>Diſobedience.</hi> Let us then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the late Actings of theſe Gentlemen with a Notion we find in an Admired
<note n="*" place="margin">A Letter containing Reflections on His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> Pamphlet, Written by one of their own Communion, and we may ſee Cauſe juſtly to conclude, that they eſteem the Exerciſe of the <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> to be a Subverſion of the Whole Government, <hi>Which</hi> (to uſe the Author's own Words) <hi>being ſo contrary to the Truſt that is given to the PRINCE, who ought to Execute it, will put Men upon</hi> Uneaſie <hi>and</hi> Dangerous <hi>Enquiries, which will turn Little to the Advantage of thoſe who are driving Matters to ſuch a</hi> Doubtful <hi>and</hi> Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Iſſue. To which let us add, That this is mention'd in Contradiſtinction to the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſisting Doctrine;</hi> and then conſider, Whether any rational Man (who is acquainted with what theſe very men do, to fill the Minds of His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Subjects with <hi>Diſcontent,</hi>) can think, that by <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> they mean
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93197:32"/>any thing leſs than ſome Methods, better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>ſilenced</hi> than <hi>expreſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When the Proteſtant Diſſenters went not half ſo far in their Diſobedience to the Regal Authority, they could not eſcape the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of being Enemies to the Government, and were immediately made uncapable of any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice. They only refuſed to Subſcribe unto two of the three Articles, and this was interpreted a Renouncing the <hi>KING</hi>'s Supreme Authority in Matters Eccleſiaſtical, and without the Aid of an Act of Parliament they were deprived.</p>
                  <p>And whoever carefully obſerves the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick Proceedings, will find, That when the Eccleſiaſtical Judges deal with Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, they never give over till there be either a Submiſſion, or a running the Offender to the Laſt Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Thus, if a Man did but abſent himſelf from the Sacrament, and was admoniſhed, he muſt Conform, or be run to an Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and at laſt to the Writ <hi>de Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicato
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93197:33"/>capiendo.</hi> In like manner, if any of the Clergy fell under the Cenſure of Suſpenſion <hi>ab Officio,</hi> unleſs there had been a Submiſſion, it went on to a Suſpenſion <hi>à Beneficio;</hi> yea, and to a Deprivation: Which, if done in one Dioceſs, was to be regarded by every Dioceſan throughout the whole Kingdom. And the Reaſon our Clergy give for this, is not the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the Offenders, but a Reducing 'em to the Knowledge of themſelves, and a due Submiſſion to their Superiors; whoſe Part it is to ſecure the Great Ends of Government; as alſo, for the diſcouraging Others from the like Miſcarriages. And on this account it is, that the making the <hi>Magdalen-Fellows</hi> uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices, Dignities, or Promotions, became <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> it being no more than what is included in every De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of the Clergy. And for this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the KING's Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have made the enſuing Decree.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="decree">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:93197:33"/>
                        <head>By His MAJESTY's Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes,</hi> and for <hi>Viſiting the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and all and every Cathedral,</hi> and <hi>Collegiate Churches, Colledges, Grammar-Schools,</hi> and <hi>other the like Incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> or <hi>Foundations,</hi> and <hi>Societies.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHereas, We thought Fit by Our Order, of the</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> 
                           <hi>of</hi> June <hi>laſt, to Declare, and Decree, That the Pretended Election of Mr.</hi> John Hough (<hi>now Dr.</hi> John Tough) <hi>to the Preſidentſhip of St.</hi> Mary Magdalen <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Oxon, <hi>was Void, and therefore did amove the ſaid Mr.</hi> Hough <hi>from the Place of Preſident of the ſaid Colledge; And whereas the Fellows of the ſame were likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened before Us for their Diſobedience to, and Contempt of His MAJESTY's Authority, by making the ſaid Pretended Election, and it now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing unto Us, That the ſaid Dr.</hi> John Tough, <hi>Dr.</hi> Charles Aldeworth, <hi>Dr.</hi> Henry Fairfax, <hi>Dr.</hi> Alexander Pudſey, <hi>Dr.</hi> John Smith, <hi>Dr.</hi> Thomas Bayley, <hi>Dr.</hi> Hhomas Stafford, Mr. Robert Almont, Mr. Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93197:34"/>Hammond, Mr. John Rogers, Mr. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Strickland, Mr. Henry Dobſon, Mr. James Bayley, Mr. John Davies, Mr. Francis Bagſhaw, Mr. James Fayrer, Mr. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Harwar, Mr. Thomas Bateman, Mr. George Hunt, Mr. William Cradock, Mr. John Gillman, Mr. George Fulham, Mr. Charles Penyſton, Mr. Robert Hyde, Mr. Edward Yerbury, Mr. Henry Holden, <hi>and</hi> Mr. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Weelks, <hi>Lately Fellows of the ſaid Colledge, do</hi> perſiſt in their Diſobedience <hi>and</hi> Contempt; <hi>We have thought Fit, upon Mature Conſideration of the Matter, to Declare, Decree, and Pronounce, And We do accordingly Declare, Decree, and Pronounce, That the ſaid Dr.</hi> John Hough, <hi>&amp;c. and every of Them, ſhall be, &amp; from henceforth they are hereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; adjudged Incapable of Receiving, or being Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, Benefice, or Promotion; and that ſuch, and every of them, who are not as yet in Holy Orders, ſhall be, and are hereby Declared and Adjudged incapable of Receiving, or being Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the ſame; And all Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſtical Officers and Miniſters within the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>are hereby required to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of This Our Sentence, Order, and Decree, and to yield Obedience thereunto.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under Our Seal <date>
                                 <hi>the</hi> 10th. <hi>of</hi> December, 1687.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:93197:34"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THUS You have a Juſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given You of the Proceedings of His <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi>'s Commiſſioners, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors, with the KING's Power in Matters Eccleſiaſtical; How, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Church of <hi>England-Law,</hi> His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> can Diſpenſe, not only with <hi>College-Statutes,</hi> but with <hi>Provincial Canons,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> And yet how Unjuſtly the Fellows Oppoſed the KING's Supremacy, to which they are All Sworn, and which, they ſhould have Regarded after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner than they did; As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with what Contempt, and Scorn,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93197:35"/>they Carryed it towards His <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi>'s Viſitors; Giving them Opprobrious Language, and making Falſe Reports of Matter of Fact, intending to fill the Minds of the KING's Subjects with Fears, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, and Diſcontent: ſo that, on the whole, an Ordinary Capacity may with much clearneſs perceive, That His <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, have in their Proceedings againſt the <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Fellows kept within the Bounds of <hi>Justice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, notwithſtanding any thing the Commiſſioners have done, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>Magdalen</hi> College, His <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi>'s <hi>Clemency</hi> toward the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſurprizing, and cannot but appear ſo to any that do but mind what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93197:35"/>mention'd about the Opinion of the Judges, which was, <hi>That the</hi> KING <hi>without a Parliament can make Ordinances and Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Government</hi> of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and Deprive them if they Obey not. To which, let us Add, That this was the very End, for which the Judges Opinion was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, <hi>viz.</hi> The Juſtifying the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Depriving the Old Puritans for not Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to the Ceremonies enjoyned by the Canon; thereby plainly ſhewing, that the KING without a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may appoint what Ceremonies He pleaſe.</p>
               <p>Now it's not to be doubted, That if His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> would but Exerciſe this Power in Matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, he might Appoint and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93197:36"/>Ordain ſo many Ceremonies, and Require Subſcription to them, as would make the Church of <hi>England</hi> look exactly like that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Deprive all thoſe that dare Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey.</p>
               <p>Let us but Conſider then, with what Severity the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>-Clergy expreſs themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery: and again, Obſerve how eaſily the KING might by their own Law, impoſe a very great Part of <hi>It</hi> on them, and deprive them, if they Obey not; and 'twill not be difficult to conclude, what would be the condition of theſe Preſent Sticklers againſt Popery. To the Sign of the Croſs in Baptiſm, the KING might enjoyn Exſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flation, Salt, and Spittle; and to Kneeling at the Sacrament, the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93197:36"/>Deacons Kiſſing of the Hand, or Right Shoulder of the Prieſt, and the Mens Kiſſing each other; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Holy Water, and it's Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, as well as the Conſecration of Churches; and a hundred ſuch things more might His MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY, enjoyn the Clergy, and thereby make it neceſſary for Our Clergy to Subſcribe unto all theſe, to the Opening the Mouths of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> againſt them, or to Feel what a Deprivation is.</p>
               <p>But His MAJESTY, to the end He may convince the moſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Enemies to His Government, is Reſolv'd to Proceed in the calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Way; and therefore, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the moſt Undutiful, and Diſloyal Reflections Caſt on MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY It ſelf, by ſome of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93197:37"/>Church of <hi>England;</hi> It's His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Purpoſe, That His Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall not Exerciſe that Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt them, which they have againſt <hi>Protestant-Diſſenters;</hi> Nor will His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> take thoſe Advantages againſt their Clergy, which He might: He is rather for the more Peaceable and Chriſtian Methods, and therefore will do the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> no more Hurt, than to give Eaſe unto Others: And nothing but a moſt Violent Provocation, can Overcome Him to Alter this Method.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:93197:37"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
